Finding Aid for Jabez Thomas Sunderland Papers 1868-1936
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jabez Thomas Sunderland papers 1868-1936
Sunderland, Jabez Thomas, 1842-1936.
Unitarian minister, anti-imperialist, and advocate of independence for India. Extensive professional and family correspondence, diaries, sermons, manuscripts of books and articles, research notes, topical file on India, printed material, newspaper clippings, and miscellanea; also papers concerning his career first as a Baptist minister, later a Unitarian minister in Ann Arbor, Michigan and elsewhere, including his involvement in the Western Unitarian Conference.
86485 Aa 2; UAm
49.4 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The Sunderland papers were donated by Mrs. Alice Sunderland Wethy (donor no. 3061 ) in 1972. The papers also contain material donated by Mrs. Janet Toohy Ferguson (donor no. 9192 ) in 2002. Additional materials were donated by David Sunderland Wethy (donor no. 10888 ) in 2013.
The collection is open for research.
Jabez Thomas Sunderland (1842-1936) was an influential Unitarian minister and a leading anti-imperialist in the late-nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. He was born in Yorkshire, England, but his family soon moved to the United States where he was educated at the University of Chicago (A.B., 1867; A.M., 1869) and the Baptist Union Theological Seminary (B.D., 1870).
Sunderland entered the Baptist ministry even before he finished his seminary work and served churches in Omaha and Milwaukee. By 1872, his liberal religious beliefs caused him to leave the Baptist church and accept a position with the Unitarian church of Northfield, Massachusetts. He stayed in Northfield for four years and then served as minister at Unitarian churches in Chicago (1876-1878), Ann Arbor (1878-1898), Oakland, California (1898-1899), London, England (1900-1901), Toronto, Canada (1901-1907), Hartford, Connecticut (1907-1911), Ottawa, Canada (1912-1913) and Poughkeepsie, New York (1914-1927).
The Sunderland papers are very complete for the early years of his career (1868-1887). The collection is divided into the following thirteen series: Correspondence, undated and 1868-1936, Visual Materials, Student papers and notebooks, Church and Ministerial Activities, Western Unitarian Conference, Diaries, Notebooks, etc., Sermon file, Manuscripts of Books and Articles, Research Notes and Manuscripts, Printed Materials, Topical Files on India, Miscellaneous Papers and Notebooks, Biographical/Autobiographical Material, and Topical File.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Clergy--United States.; First Unitarian Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Imperialism.; India.; Sunderland, Jabez Thomas, 1842-1936.; Unitarian churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Unitarian Universalist churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Universalist churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Western Unitarian Conference.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Burlington University.; Families--1903.; India.; Jowai (India); Sunderland, Eliza Read, 1839-1910.; Sunderland, Jabez Thomas, 1842-1936.; Unitarian Universalist churches--India.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Prisoners and prisons.; University of Chicago.
Contributors:
Abernethy, Alonzo, 1836-1915.; Aked, Charles Frederic, 1864-1941.; Allen, Joseph Henry, 1820-1898.; American Anti-Imperialist League.; American League to Limit Armaments.; Ames, Charles Gordon, 1828-1912.; Andrews, C. F. (Charles Freer), 1871-1940.; Angell, George T. (George Thorndike), 1823-1909.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Bagley, John Judson, 1832-1881.; Baldwin, William Henry, 1826-1909.; Batchelor, George, 1836-1923.; Blackwell, Alice Stone, 1857-1950.; Bose, Jagadis Chandra, 1858-1937.; Bose, Sudhindra, 1883-; Bowie, W. Copeland (William Copeland); Brigham, Charles H. (Charles Henry), 1820-1879.; Canada India League.; Chadwick, John White, 1840-1904.; Chapin, Augusta J., d. 1905.; Chatterjee, Ramananda, 1865-1943.; Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888.; Collyer, Robert, 1823-1912.; Cooke, George Willis, 1848-1923.; Crane, Augustus Warren, 1868-1937.; Crane, Caroline Bartlett, 1858-1935.; Crooker, Joseph Henry, 1850-1931.; Das, Taraknath, 1884-1958.; De Normandie, James, 1836-1924.; Drummond, James, 1835-1924.; Durant, Will, 1885-1981.; Eliot, Samuel Atkins, 1862-1950.; Everett, Charles Carroll, 1829-1900.; Ferris, Woodbridge N., 1853-1928.; Foote, Henry Wilder, 1875-1964.; Friends of Freedom for India.; Friends of India's Independence.; Gandhi, Mahatma, 1869-1948.; Gannett, Lewis, 1891-1966.; Gannett, William C. (William Channing), 1840-1923.; Garrison, William Lloyd, 1838-1909.; Gregg, Richard Bartlett, 1885-; Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909.; Hay, John, 1838-1905.; Herford, Brooke, 1830-1903.; Hindustan Association of America.; Hoar, George Frisbie, 1826-1904.; Holmes, John Haynes, 1879-1964.; India Academy of America.; India Independence League of America.; Indian National Congress. American Branch.; India Society of America.; Indian Independence League.; Ingersoll, Robert Green, 1833-1899.; Jackson, Helen Hunt, 1830-1885.; Japan Society (New York, N.Y.); Jones, Jenkin Lloyd, 1843-1918.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931.; King, Judson, 1872-1958.; Krishna Menon, V. K. (Vengalil Krishnan), 1897-1974.; Ladd, George Trumbull, 1842-1921.; Lajpat Rai, Lala, 1865-1928.; Mabie, Henry Clay, 1847-1918.; McMillan, James, 1838-1902.; Manny, Frank Addison, 1868-1954.; Martineau, James, 1805-1900.; Mead, Edwin Doak, 1849-1937.; Mead, Lucia True Ames, 1856-1936.; Michigan Authors' Association.; Morehouse, Henry Lyman, 1834-1917.; National Liberal League.; Nehru, Jawaharlal, 1889-1964.; Northrup, George Washington, 1826-1900.; Palmer, Thomas Witherell, 1830-1913.; Peabody, Francis Greenwood, 1847-1936.; Phelps, Myron H. (Myron Henry), 1856-1916.; Reid, Gilbert, 1857-1927.; Reid, Whitelaw, 1837-1912.; Savage, Minot Judson, 1841-1918.; Schurz, Carl, 1829-1906.; Shippen, Joseph, 1839-1923.; Shippen, Rush Rhees, b. 1828.; Simmons, Henry Martyn, b. 1841.; Singh, Hajom Kissor, 1865-1923.; Society for the Advancement of India.; Strong, Sydney, 1860-1938.; Sumner, William Graham, 1840-1910.; Tagore, Rabindranath, 1861-1941.; Toy, Crawford Howell, 1836-1919.; Villard, Fanny Garrison, 1844-1928.; Villard, Oswald Garrison, 1872-1949.; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915.; Wendte, Charles W. (Charles William), 1844-1931.; Willard, Frances E. (Frances Elizabeth), 1839-1898.; Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891.; Winslow, Erving, 1839-1922.; Wise, Stephen S. (Stephen Samuel), 1874-1949.
Genre/Form:
Albums.; Diaries.; Photographs.; Portraits.; Scrapbooks.; Sermons.
- Correspondence undated, 1868-1936
  Sunderland's correspondence consists of both professional and family correspondence.
  The professional correspondence, especially for the years 1868-1887, delineates many of the problems and successes of the Unitarian church in the second half of the nineteenth century. Of interest is the correspondence for 1885 and 1886 when Sunderland served as general secretary of the Western Unitarian Conference and western agent of the American Unitarian Association. During this time the theological question known as "The Issue in the West" was debated heatedly in the annual church meetings. On this issue Sunderland differed with many of the other young ministers in the Western Unitarian Conference and supported the retention of a theistic basis for Unitarianism.
  Some of Sunderland's correspondents during this period include J.H. Allen, Charles G. Ames, William H. Baldwin, John W. Chadwick, James Freeman Clarke, Robert Collyer, George W. Cooke, Joseph H. Crooker, James De Normandie, William C. Gannett, Edward Everett Hale, Brooke Herford, Robert G. Ingersoll, Jenkin Lloyd Jones, Minot J. Savage, Joseph Shippen, Rush R. Shippen and Charles W. Wendte.
  In 1895 the British Unitarian Association sent Sunderland to India to report on the educational, social and religious conditions of the Indian people. As a result of this trip to India, Sunderland became a firm anti-imperialist, spending much of the rest of his career advocating independence for India. Sunderland made a subsequent trip to India in 1913. His correspondence files include exchanges with such Indians as Sir J.C. Bose, Sudhindra Bose, Ramananda Chatterjee, Taraknath Das, Mahatma Gandhi, Lala Lajpat Rai, Hajom Kissor Singh, and Rabindranath Tagore.
  Among the Americans and Englishmen he corresponded with on the questions of India and anti-imperialism are Charles F. Andrews, Alice Stone Blackwell, W. Copeland Bowie, Will Durant, William Lloyd Garrison Jr., Richard B. Gregg, John Haynes Holmes, Myron H. Phelps, Oswald Garrison Villard and Erving Winslow. He also had contacts with such groups as the Society for the Advancement of India, the Hindustan Association of America and the American branch of the India National Congress.
  In addition to Sunderland's professional correspondence, which is relatively weak for the periods 1888 to 1897, 1901 to 1906, and 1912 to 1926, the collection contains extensive family correspondence covering the years 1868 to 1910, with a few scattered letters after that time. Since the professional correspondence consists almost entirely of incoming letters, Sunderland's letters and postcards to his wife and children and the diaries which have been saved for some years are the only source for discovering his thoughts on various issues and events.
  In addition to the personal correspondence in this collection, more of Sunderland's letters to his family can be in the papers of his wife, Eliza Jane Read Sunderland, his son Edson Read Sunderland, his daughter Florence Sunderland, and in the Sunderland-Safford family collection, which include the papers of Sunderland's first daughter, Gertrude Sunderland Safford. This last collection is especially rich in Sunderland family correspondence.
  - By date
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - January 1868-November 1878, 34 folders (Box 1)
    - December 1878-December 1885, 31 folders (Box 2)
    - January 1886-May 1900, 46 folders (Box 3)
    - June 1900-1915, 36 folders (Box 4)
    - 1916-December 1934, 38 folders (Box 5)
    - 1935-1936, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Fragmentary letterbook 1886-1891 (Box 6)
  - Letter from J.H. Cafnon to Mrs. Jane B. Read (mother of Eliza Sunderland) 1846 (Box 6)
  - Family correspondence
    - Undated 1868 (Box 6)
    - 1869-December 1889, 30 folders (Box 6)
    - January 1890-December 1900, 24 folders (Box 7)
    - January 1901-March 1906, 26 folders (Box 8)
    - April 1906-1934, 28 folders (Box 9)
- Visual Materials
  - Scrapbook/Photograph Album relating to Burlington University and the University of Chicago 1860-1870 (Box 10)
    (includes photo of Civil War prison camp)
  - Photographs, 6 folders (Box 10)
    (includes portraits; photo of Ann Arbor Unitarian Church; photos of views of India; Indian acquaintances, institutions, and customs)
    (see also oversize folder, UAm)
- Student papers and notebooks
  - Studies at the University of Chicago 1867-1870, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Notebooks from courses taken at the University of Chicago 1867-1870, 9 volumes (Box 10)
- Church and Ministerial Activities
  - Pastorates in Omaha, Milwaukee and Northfield, Massachusetts 1870-1876 (Box 10)
  - Sunderland sermons published in Chicago newspapers 1876-1878, 6 folders (Box 10)
  - First Unitarian Church of Ann Arbor 1878-1898, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Michigan Unitarian Conference 1878-1898 (Box 10)
  - Articles and newspaper clippings 1878-1898, 4 folders (Box 11)
  - Notebooks concerning the building of the Ann Arbor Unitarian Church and other historical matters 1882-1894 (Box 11)
    (includes letters from Freeman Clarke, Edward Everett Hale and Rev. J.H. Allen)
  - Scrapbooks concerning subscription for A College Town Pulpit and Pacific Coast Pulpit, 1878-1898 (Box 11)
  - Record book of Ann Arbor baptisms and funerals 1878-1898 (Box 11)
    (includes membership list of Fourth Unitarian Church in Chicago)
  - First Unitarian Church of Oakland, California 1898-1899, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Highgate Unitarian Church in London, England 1900 (Box 11)
  - First Unitarian Church in Toronto, Canada 1901-1906
    - Scrapbook (Box 11)
    - Papers, 4 folders (Box 12)
  - Unity Church in Hartford, Connecticut 1906-1911, 6 folders (Box 12)
  - Papers supporting Sunderland's ministry at Hartford 1906 (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook concerning Unity Church in Hartford, Connecticut 1906-1911 (Box 12)
  - Church of Our Father in Ottawa, Canada 1912-1913, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Papers concerning his trip to India 1913-1914, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Unitarian Church of Poughkeepsie, New York 1914-1929, 5 folders (Box 12)
- Western Unitarian Conference
  - Theological divisions in the Western Unitarian Conference 1880-1894, 14 folders (Box 13)
  - Theological divisions in the Western Unitarian Conference (printed material) 1872-1887, 5 folders (Box 13)
  - Theological divisions in the Western Unitarian Conference (newspaper clippings) 1880-1891, 3 folders (Box 13)
- Diaries, Notebooks, etc.
  - Address books (Box 14)
  - Books lent (Box 14)
  - Cash book for The Unitarian, 1886-1888 (Box 14)
  - Cash book for The Unitarian, 1888-1897 (Box 14)
  - Ledger 1872-1884 (Box 14)
    (includes records, 1859-1860 of the Euepian Society at Burlington University)
  - Personal accounts, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Record book of marriages, funerals and christenings 1899-1911 (Box 14)
  - Diaries
    - 1865-1866 (Box 14)
    - 1870-1871 (Box 14)
    - 1872 (Box 14)
    - 1874 (Box 14)
    - 1884-1885, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - 1889 (Box 14)
      (travel to England and Europe, with partial transcript)
    - 1891-1892 (Box 14)
    - 1892-1894 (Box 14)
    - 1895-1896 (Box 48)
      (5 folders, travel to England, Europe, the Middle East, and India)
    - 1897-1898 (Box 48)
    - 1901-1904 (Box 48)
    - 1907 (Box 48)
    - 1909-1912 (Box 48)
    - 1913-1914 (Box 48)
      (2 folders, travel to East Asia and India)
    - 1915-1915 (Box 48)
    - 1918-1920 (Box 48)
    - 1921-1923 (Box 48)
    - 1924-1926 (Box 48)
    - 1927-1929 (Box 48)
    - 1932 (Box 48)
      ("Suggestions and topics for autobiography")
- Sermon file
  (arranged by date)
  - Mr. Miln and Unitarianism undated (Box 15)
  - The Mystery of Life undated (Box 15)
  - The Moral Value of Belief in Immortality undated (Box 15)
  - He That Hath Seen Me, Hath Seen the Father undated (Box 15)
  - Doctrine and Life undated (Box 15)
  - Let Love Be Without Dissimulation undated (Box 15)
  - Garrison and the Struggle to Abolish Slavery in America undated (Box 15)
  - All These Things Are Against Me 1867 (Box 15)
  - Christ, a King 1868 (Box 15)
  - One Thing Thou Lackest 1870 (Box 15)
  - Unto the Pure, All Things Are Pure 1871 (Box 15)
  - I Pray Thee, Have Me Excused 1871 (Box 15)
  - Be Ye Therefore Perfect, Even as Your Father in Heaven in Perfect 1871 (Box 15)
  - The Chicago, Boston and Northwestern Fires 1871 (Box 15)
  - Whether Therefore Ye Eat or Drink or Whatsoever Ye Do, Do All to the Glory of God 1871 (Box 15)
  - Relation of the Bible to the State 1872 (Box 15)
  - Prodigal Son 1872 (Box 15)
  - The Feminine Element in Theology and Religion 1872 (Box 15)
  - Report on the General Conference held in Boston 1872 (Box 15)
  - The Interpretation of the Old Testament 1872 (Box 15)
  - How Shall We Spend Our Sabbaths 1872 (Box 15)
  - The Kingdom of God Cometh Not With Outward Show 1872 (Box 15)
  - The Tongue (Children's Sermon) 1872 (Box 15)
  - The Responsibility of Parents With Reference to the Religious Education of Their Children 1872 (Box 15)
  - More Blessed to Give Than to Receive 1873 (Box 15)
  - Wonderful Things to be Seen in Northfield (Children's Sermon) 1873 (Box 15)
  - Inscrutable Providence 1873 (Box 15)
  - Consider the Lilies of the Field, How They Grow 1873 (Box 15)
  - Pieces of Folks (Children's Sermon) 1873 (Box 15)
  - Recognition of Friends in Heaven 1873 (Box 15)
  - The Life That Now Is 1873 (Box 15)
  - Epidemics of the Mind 1873 (Box 15)
  - Never Man Spoke Like This Man 1873 (Box 15)
  - The Panic 1873 (Box 15)
  - Lessons Deduced From Sermons on the Future Life 1873 (Box 15)
  - Making the Most of Life 1873 (Box 15)
  - Sunday School Anniversary Sermon 1873 (Box 15)
  - God's Silence 1873 (Box 15)
  - Anniversary Sermon 1873 (Box 15)
  - True, or Christian, Liberty 1874 (Box 15)
  - The Higher Uses of Intelligence 1874 (Box 15)
  - In What Sense is Jesus a Saviour 1874 (Box 15)
  - What's in a Name 1874 (Box 15)
  - Ten Times One are Ten (Children's Sermon) 1874 (Box 15)
  - Whatsoever Thy hand Findeth to Do, Do it With Thy Might, (Children's Sermon) 1874 (Box 15)
  - Sermon on Temperance 1874 (Box 15)
  - Tweedledees and Tweedledums in Religion 1874 (Box 15)
  - Anniversary Sermon 1874 (Box 16)
  - Some Conditions of Happiness 1875 (Box 16)
  - Education and Other Improvements Needed in the Town 1875 (Box 16)
  - Son Remember 1875 (Box 16)
  - Work 1875 (Box 16)
  - Amusements 1875 (Box 16)
  - Hurting and Healing Shadows 1875 (Box 16)
  - Salvation By the Truth 1875 (Box 16)
  - Righteousness 1875, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Be Still and Listen 1875 (Box 16)
  - The Ideal Christian Church 1875 (Box 16)
  - The Better Religion Coming 1876 (Box 16)
  - Reasons for Not Fearing Death 1876 (Box 16)
  - Moody's and Sankey's Success 1876 (Box 16)
  - Some Religious Lessons to be Learned from Scientists 1876 (Box 16)
  - What is Unitarianism 1876 (Box 16)
  - Revivals 1876 (Box 16)
  - The Scope and Limitations of the Pulpit 1876 (Box 16)
  - The Religious Duty of Prevention of Disease and Preserving Health 1876 (Box 16)
  - Life's Important Choices 1876 (Box 16)
  - Do This In Remembrance of Me 1876 (Box 16)
  - Real Infidelity 1877 (Box 16)
  - The Value of the Church 1877 (Box 16)
  - Duties and Responsibilities of Educated Men 1877 (Box 16)
  - The Perils of Majorities 1877 (Box 16)
  - Professor Swing's Sermon Last Sunday 1877 (Box 16)
  - It is Written Again 1877 (Box 16)
  - Hints and Foregleams of the Future World 1877 (Box 16)
  - The Relation of Knowledge to Faith 1877 (Box 16)
  - Living for Others 1877 (Box 16)
  - The Power of the Imagination 1877 (Box 17)
  - Heredity 1877, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - What is Religion 1877 (Box 17)
  - Sectarianism Never to be Cured Till Orthodoxy is Destroyed 1877 (Box 17)
  - The Devil 1877 (Box 17)
  - The Relation of Knowledge to Virtue 1877 (Box 17)
  - The Inclusiveness of True Christianity 1877 (Box 17)
  - Bear Ye One Another's Burdens 1877 (Box 17)
  - Why Young Men Had better Not Drink Liquor 1878 (Box 17)
  - The Increase of Faith 1878 (Box 17)
  - Reasons Why We Do Not Fast and Keep Lent 1878 (Box 17)
  - Sermon on Leaving Chicago 1878 (Box 17)
  - Sermon on Memorial and Flower Sunday 1878 (Box 17)
  - Is Life Worth Living 1878 (Box 17)
  - Robert Ingersoll 1878 (Box 17)
  - Everlasting Punishment 1878 (Box 17)
  - The New Aim of the Church 1879 (Box 17)
  - Was Jesus God 1879 (Box 17)
  - Insincerity in Religion 1879 (Box 17)
  - The Resurrection of Jesus 1879 (Box 17)
  - Homes 1879 (Box 17)
  - Talmadge as a Sign of the Times 1879 (Box 18)
  - History of Unitarianism in Europe 1879 (Box 18)
  - Every Plant 1880 (Box 18)
  - Hell, Future Punishment, Heaven 1880 (Box 18)
  - Materialistic and Other Objections to the Doctrine of a Future Life 1880 (Box 18)
  - Immortality in this World 1880 (Box 18)
  - The Story of Unitarianism in America 1880 (Box 18)
  - Review of Joseph Cook's Lecture 1880 (Box 18)
  - A Study of Creeds 1880 (Box 18)
  - The Religion of Doing Good 1880 (Box 18)
  - Choosing a Vocation 1880 (Box 18)
  - Dr. Chapin 1880 (Box 18)
  - The Lessons of the Meeting of the American Social Science Association 1881 (Box 18)
  - The Desire for Infallibilities in Religion 1881 (Box 18)
  - The Power of Circumstance 1881 (Box 18)
  - The Life to Come 1882 (Box 18)
  - Conscience 1882 (Box 18)
  - Preparation Against Old Age 1882 (Box 18)
  - The End of the World and the Day of Judgement 1882 (Box 18)
  - Religious Reform 1882 (Box 18)
  - Lame From Birth 1882 (Box 18)
  - The Origins of the Doctrine of the Trinity 1882 (Box 18)
  - The Depravity of Human Nature 1882 (Box 18)
  - What Knowledge is of Most Worth 1882, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Dr. D.B. Frothinghan and his Recent Utterance 1882 (Box 19)
  - Eminent Unitarian Ministers Who Have Died During the Year 1881, 1882 (Box 19)
  - A Study of Evangelicalism, Ritualism and Rationalism 1883 (Box 19)
  - Man, Human Nature, the Fall, Depravity, Sin 1883 (Box 19)
  - The Larger Meaning of Unitarianism 1883 (Box 19)
  - What Are Unitarian Churches For 1883 (Box 19)
  - Annual Sermon 1883 (Box 19)
  - The Hand (Children's Sermon) 1884 (Box 19)
  - Worship of Intellect 1886, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Why I Believe in Immortality 1890 (Box 19)
  - The Soul's Cry for God 1891 (Box 19)
  - Messianic Prophecy 1891 (Box 19)
  - The Roman Catholic Congress of Religions 1892 (Box 19)
  - George William Curtis 1892 (Box 19)
  - Christmas 1892 (Box 19)
  - Poets and Liberal Religion 1893, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - One Sure Way of Doing Good 1895 (Box 19)
  - General Old Testament Prophecy 1895 (Box 19)
  - The Religion of Eminent Men 1895 (Box 19)
  - More Abundant Life 1897 (Box 19)
  - The Real and the Ideal 1897 (Box 19)
  - The Ministry of Sorrow 1898 (Box 19)
  - Working Together With God 1898, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Why We Have No Creed 1898 (Box 19)
  - The Worth of Man 1898, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Ralph Waldo Emerson 1899 (Box 20)
  - Sermons Which Children Teach Us 1900 (Box 20)
  - After Vacation Thoughts 1901 (Box 20)
  - Unconscious Influence 1901 (Box 20)
  - Overcome Evil With Good 1902 (Box 20)
  - The Divine Incarnation 1902, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - The Larger View of Revelation and Inspiration 1902 (Box 20)
  - The Second Coming of Christ 1902, 5 folders (Box 20)
  - A Safe Religion 1902 (Box 20)
  - Sectarianism 1902 (Box 20)
  - Beautiful Lives in Humble Places 1902 (Box 20)
  - The New Thought of Conversion 1903 (Box 20)
  - Music 1903 (Box 20)
  - The Value and Uses of Sunday 1903 (Box 20)
  - True Riches 1903 (Box 20)
  - The True Greatness of Men and Nations 1904 (Box 20)
  - The Beauty and Sacredness of Duty 1904 (Box 20)
  - Atheism 1905 (Box 20)
  - Religious Pioneership 1905, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Life's Dreams 1905 (Box 21)
  - More Blessed to Give than Receive 1906 (Box 21)
  - Nature 1906 (Box 21)
  - Is Nature Cruel 1906 (Box 21)
  - Who Are Christians 1906 (Box 21)
  - War-Will it Ever Cease 1906 (Box 21)
  - The Human Jesus 1907 (Box 21)
  - A Religion to Die By 1907 (Box 21)
  - A Religion to Live and Die By 1908 (Box 21)
  - The Heroic Spirit 1908 (Box 21)
  - The New Thought of Man 1908 (Box 21)
  - The New Thought of Heaven and Hell 1908 (Box 21)
  - The New Thought of Salvation 1909 (Box 21)
  - Bread from Heaven 1910 (Box 21)
  - Loyalty to Conviction 1912 (Box 21)
  - The True Law of Retribution and Reward 1912 (Box 21)
  - Casting Out Devils 1913 (Box 21)
  - The Great Sacred Books of Mankind 1914 (Box 21)
  - Is Inquiry in Religion Safe 1914 (Box 21)
  - The New Thought of Religion 1916 (Box 21)
  - Bayard Taylor 1916 (Box 21)
  - Will Mankind Ever Outgrow Religion 1916 (Box 21)
  - William Cullen Bryant 1919 (Box 21)
  - The Modernist View of the Bible 1920 (Box 21)
  - The Great and Unparalleled Affirmations of the Unitarian Faith 1924, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Knowing By Doing 1926 (Box 22)
  - What is Truth 1926 (Box 22)
  - Orthodoxy: An Enemy of Christianity 1926 (Box 22)
- Manuscripts of Books and Articles
  (arranged alphabetically)
  - Because Men Are Not Stones 1923 (Box 22)
  - The Best Books on India (Box 22)
  - The Best in the Bible (Box 22)
  - The Bible, 5 folders (Box 22)
  - The Bible in the Light of Modern Knowledge (Box 22)
  - The British in India (Box 22)
  - British Justice and Law in India (Box 22)
  - The Causes of Famines in India 1904 (Box 22)